<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>ÿþ&lt;<Esri><CreaDate>20080130</CreaDate><CreaTime>10402000</CreaTime><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><SyncDate>20050330</SyncDate><SyncTime>15041800</SyncTime><ModDate>20050330</ModDate><ModTime>15041800</ModTime><MetaID>{396E5EB8-9606-48FA-9102-94F6DEDF960A}</MetaID></Esri><dataqual><lineage><procstep><procdesc>1) PHOTOGRAPHIC DATA SOURCES &amp; PROCEDURES

Kelp aerial photography was acquired from three sources:

DFG Air Services:

Aerial photos were taken in October, November, and December of 1999 with a medium format (60 mm) Hasselblad camera with an 80mm lens from an altitude of 11,000 feet above sea level.  A Global Positioning System receiver (Garmin GPS12XL) was used to capture the aircraft's position at the exposure station of each photo.  The developed photo frames (scale 1:41000 or 1" = approximately 3400', color, infrared transparency) were annotated with consecutive ID numbers.  Every fifth frame was additionally labeled with local time and date of exposure (from the GPS data).  An ArcView shapefile (see \shapefiles\KELP99FG.shp) including the plotted photo points and table of photo data was created to index all photography.  A logical (yes/no) value was also added to the table for identifying kelp presence or absence in each photo.


I.K. Curtis Services

Aerial photos were taken in October and November of 1999 with Wild RC10 and RC20 aerial mapping cameras (industry-standard, 6" lens with 9"x9" film format).  The resultant color infrared contact prints were supplied to DFG labeled with date, original scale (1:24000 or 1"=2000'), time, and photo ID.  A GPS-based, photo-center index was also supplied by the contractor.  DFG converted the index into an ArcView shapefile (KELP99IK.shp) and added photo ID numbers and other data (as above) to the attribute table, including the administrative kelp bed number (see \documentation\kelpadmbed.txt, \shapefiles\kelpbed2.shp) that a given photo covered all or a portion thereof.


Pacific Aerial Surveys

Photos were taken in November 1999 with an industry standard Zeiss RMK TOP mapping camera (6" lens, 9"x9" format).  The resultant color, infrared contact prints were supplied to DFG labeled with date, scale (1:24000), time and photo ID number.  As in the previous two photography sets, an ArcView point shapefile was created (\shapefiles\KELP99PA.shp) to index each photo; the date and time were added manually to the table as well as a logical (yes/no) value for kelp presence/absence per frame.


AERIAL PHOTO SCANNING PROCEDURES

DFG photos were scanned at 700 dots-per-inch (dpi), whereas the IK Curtis and Pacific Aerial photos were scanned at 400 dpi.  All were saved as standard .jpg files.  While the scan resolution was greater (and the original scale smaller) for the DFG photos versus the contractor photos, the approximate ground pixel size is 2 meters for all photography.  The raw digital images were saved to CDROM disks (see \documentation\cd_photolist.xls).  Processing priority was given to kelp-bearing photos, so presently, there are some gaps in the coastwide, digital versions of the photography. 


GEOREFERENCING THE AERIAL PHOTOGRAPHS

The process of using digital aerial photography in a GIS requires a processing step known as registration or georeferencing.  Aerial photographs have a nominal scale, but that scale is not constant throughout the frame.  This registration process attempts to correct for scale changes, as well as to add an earth-coordinate system, thereby allowing other digital layers with similar spatial coordinate systems to be co-registered with the photography.  There are several methods for performing the registration process and various levels of accuracy associated with each method.  

The 1999 kelp survey employed two registration methods.  In the initial phase of the project, photogrammetric processes were used ERDAS Orthobase, version 8.4.  This process employs camera parameters(see \documentation\camera parameters), camera orientation and position, and corrects for scale changes due to terrain elevational changes.  Excellent results in the spatial accuracies throughout the photos were achieved with this technique.  The process was difficult to implement because of the nature of the photos, which were kelp-centered.  This off-shore centering of the kelp photography resulted in a minimal amount of land along the edge of the photos having identifiable features suitable as control points.  To compensate for the control point alignment along the edge of photos and parallel to the flight line, extra control points were selected which required more processing time.  Some of the pattern-matching algorithms were not as automatic as hoped, so manual selection of additional points (known as tie points) was required.  Typical Root Mean Square Errors (RMSE) on the control points was 1 - 2 meters.  Erdas Orthobase was used to perform the photogrammetric corrections.

As an alternative approach, an affine transformation was used (ArcView v3.1/Image Analysis v1.0).  This reduced the preparation time because fewer inputs were required, the user interface was easier to operate, and because the image would shift onto a basemap in real time as control point selections were made, shortening the feedback loop from input to results.  Control point selection was limited to near sea level to help ensure the target of interest (the kelp forests surface canopy) was in the same plane as were the control points.  Each control point was saved in a shapefile that also shows RMSE for each point and total RMSE value.   Typical values were in the range of 4 - 12 meters.  6 - 15 points were selected from each photo.  The photo registration was less accurate on land areas, particularly areas with steep terrain, than along the shoreline and in kelp areas.

2) KELP CLASSIFICATION METHODS:    

IMAGE NAME: k99aknnn_4cls.img, where nnn = 3 digit numeric DFG Administrative Kelp Bed Identifier.

COVERAGE DESCRIPTION

These ERDAS images represent kelp extent within each Administrative Kelp Bed, identified by number in their respective filenames.
 
ERDAS Imagine and ArcView Image Analysis were used to create an iterative, self-organizing clustering (Isodata) process to segment the image based on reflected light signatures.  These signatures were then interpreted for kelp canopy.  The parameters used in the classification include 20 spectral clusters, .95 convergence, and initial classes to be allocated along the axis of greatest variability (principle component).  Twenty spectral classes means that the "image colors" in and around the kelp bed are divided into twenty different units.  Because the algorithm is iterative in nature, the spectral locations of the clusters are adjusted with each iteration to maximize the number of pixels contained close to a spectral cluster center.  When the amount of adjustment is minimized to meet the .95 convergence and the twenty classes are created, the iteration stops.

The classes were evaluated for statistical separability.  Some adjacent classes were not separable, which is not uncommon in this type of routine.  However, the twenty classes will be merged into 4 classes.  The 1989 data was derived from methods based on already interpreted maps and methods using a binary level of kelp or not kelp.

The following describes the initial 20 class values and an interpretation based on examining the photos, and 1989 kelp information and the comparison of how those 20 classes were merged in order to generalize the classification scheme to 4 classes.  As indicated by the initial scheme, more classes were created than were needed.  This was done intentionally so that the classes would have a smaller variance, understanding that class merging would take place.

Twenty Classes     Four classes

Class# Description    Class# Description

1-9  Open Water    1  Open Water
10  Submerged Kelp   2  Low Density or Submerged Kelp
11  Open Water    1  Open Water
12  Submerged Kelp   2  Low Density or Submerged Kelp
13  Water w/ high sediment  1  Open water
14  Submerged Kelp   2  Low Density or Submerged Kelp
15  Submerged Kelp   2  Low Density or Submerged Kelp
16-18  Low-Medium Density   3  Medium Density or 
  or submerged.     submerged.
19-20  Dense Kelp at Surface  4  Dense Kelp at Surface. 

The clustering routine was initially run on mosaicked images in southern beds.  In northern beds, too much variability between photos, due to higher sediment in the water column, prevented this approach.  The clustering was run on each frame, resulting in a set of twenty classes that had unique interpretations.  The twenty classes were grouped into four and then mosaicked.
   
Final steps involved a conversion to polygon format in order to test some statistical properties.  To prepare for the conversion, the reclassified image (4 classes) was filtered.  Any isolated pixels in "bunches" of less than 8 contiguous pixels were set to background using the ERDAS sieve function.  This process was only performed on bed 3 only. Some statistics were created for patch size analysis.


3) CONVERTING FINAL CLASSIFICATION TO POLYGONS

The final 4 merged classifications were brought into ArcGIS 8.1 and the spatial analyst extension was used to convert the raster to features.  The Open Water class was excluded from this conversion.
</procdesc><date Sync="TRUE">20030303</date><time Sync="TRUE">13161300</time></procstep><srcinfo><typesrc>filmstrip</typesrc></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">U:\BCB\CA_NMS_GIS\finalshapes\Data\99kelp</srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20030327</date><time Sync="TRUE">15481400</time></procstep><procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE"></srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20050330</date><time Sync="TRUE">13581000</time></procstep><procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">V:\265_admin\lab_development\carmel_bay\Biological\kelp99_c</srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20080130</date><time Sync="TRUE">10402000</time></procstep></lineage><attracc><attraccr>The following are subjective remarks regarding the image data quality.  The quality of the 9 x 9, large format aerial photography is excellent. The quality of the 60mm, medium format photography ranges from fair to excellent due to weather and other logistical problems.  Shapefile indexes, spatial accuracy, and attribute completeness is very good, except for latitude/longitude values in some point attribute tables. 

The quality of the georeferenced images is slightly degraded in spatial resolution due to a required resampling and smoothing of the source image during the registration process.  Viewing of the original film under magnification will always be superior to digital imagery in terms of interpretive detail available.

Accuracy of registered images using ArcView Image Analysis extension is assessed based on the Root Mean Square Error (RMSE) of the affine transformation used to reproject the images.  This value was in the range of 4 - 12 meters.  Users may encounter greater registration errors withing the coastwide photography set.  Control points were selected at sea level or as near to sea level as possible.  Selection of control points in elevations above sea level introduced greater errors in the target areas of interest, the kelp, due to terrain-based photo distortions.  Large (tens of meters) horizontal registration errors may be detected in upland areas of the photography.

Accuracy of the registered images using ERDAS Orthobase is much better.  RMSE is in the neighborhood of 1-2 meters in shoreline and kelp areas.  Orthobase uses a block bundle adjustment, which is a very rigorous photogrammetric model.  This method allows for the selection of a greater variety of control points, corrects for lens distortion, camera attitude, and terrain distortion effects.  Spatial errors even in the upland areas of the photos were minimized.</attraccr></attracc><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The quality of the transformation of scanned map image coordinates to
GIS coordinates (albers) was automatically computed as root-mean-square
(RMS) values by the custom ARC/INFO software.  Values were returned for
both the X- and Y- direction as follows (all values in meters):

Parameter  RMS-X  RMS-Y
---------  -----  -----
Minimum     2.0    2.6
Maximum    25.3   35.6
Mean        7.2    8.3
Std.Dev.    4.8    5.2

Mean values conform to USGS National Map Accuracy standards (12 meters).

Administrative kelp bed numbers and boundary indicators for Bed 1 (at the
CA-Mexico border) northward through Bed 225 (Montara) are annotated on 
the original map sheets.  Kelp bed numbers 226 (San Francisco) through 312
(CA-Oregon border) are missing from the map sheets, having been established
after 1989.  Original aerial photography quality information is available 
from ECOSCAN.

The following are subjective remarks regarding the digital data quality:
Scanned image quality is very good.  Kelp features and harvest tracks are
clearly distinguishable from base data.  Legibility and line density of
the scanned images are good.  Map sheet matchlines register with less
accuracy than the RMS data would indicate.  Mismatches on the order of
50 to 60 meters were encountered.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc></dataqual><idinfo><native Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.0 (Build 2195) Service Pack 4; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</native><descript><langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata><abstract>Kelp beds along the coast of California are a critical habitat for many important sport and commercial species of invertebrates and fishes.  Kelp is also harvested by commercial and sport concerns.  Until now, kelp bed area figures used in harvest regulatory processes by the State have been based upon hardcopy maps, created from 1989 aerial photography, displaying hand drawn delineated features of the kelp canopy (see \documentation\kelp1989work.txt).  The Fall 1999 project digitally remeasured the 1989 kelp maps and established new digital methods to calculate the area of the 1999 kelp canopy based on aerial, color-infrared photographs.  The objective is to create a baseline that could be used to assess the effects of current and future use of coastal kelp.  This document describes various procedures and datasets assembled to-date.
</abstract><purpose>Until recently, kelp bed area figures used in harvest regulatory processes by the State have been based upon hardcopy maps, created from 1989 aerial photography, displaying hand drawn delineated features of the kelp canopy.  The Fall 1999 project digitally remeasured the 1989 kelp maps and established new digital methods to calculate the area of the 1999 kelp canopy based on aerial, color-infrared photographs.  The objective is to create a baseline that could be used to assess the effects of current and future use of coastal kelp.</purpose></descript><citation><citeinfo><origin>California Department of Fish &amp; Game </origin><pubdate>September 2000 </pubdate><title Sync="TRUE">kelp99_c</title><ftname Sync="TRUE">kelp99_c</ftname><geoform Sync="TRUE">vector digital data</geoform><onlink>http://www.dfg.ca.gov/mrd/index.html </onlink></citeinfo></citation><timeperd><current>ground condition</current><timeinfo><mdattim><sngdate><caldate>10/13/1999</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>12/22/1999</caldate></sngdate></mdattim></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc Sync="TRUE">-122.150156</westbc><eastbc Sync="TRUE">-121.822945</eastbc><northbc Sync="TRUE">36.981856</northbc><southbc Sync="TRUE">36.234093</southbc></bounding><lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">-191127.926113</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">-163621.630389</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">-195958.468399</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">-113410.721699</topbc></lboundng></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>REQUIRED: Reference to a formally registered thesaurus or a similar authoritative source of theme keywords.</themekt><themekey>Kelp</themekey><themekey>nearshore</themekey><themekey>holdfast</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Not to be used for legal purposes</useconst><natvform Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</natvform><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Nancy Wright</cntper><cntorg>California Department of Fish &amp; Game</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Coordinator </cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>20 Lower Ragsdale Drive #100</address><city>Monterey </city><state>CA</state><postal>93940</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>831-649-2942</cntvoice><cnttdd>831-649-2942</cnttdd><cntemail>nmwright@dfg.ca.gov </cntemail><hours>8am - 5pm PST </hours></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataIdInfo><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows 2000 Version 5.0 (Build 2195) Service Pack 4; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">kelp99_c</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></SpatRepTypCd></spatRpType><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-122.150156</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-121.822945</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">36.981856</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">36.234093</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></geoBox><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-191127.926113</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-163621.630389</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">-113410.721699</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">-195958.468399</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><metainfo><langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta><metstdn Sync="TRUE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv Sync="TRUE">FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntper>REQUIRED: The person responsible for the metadata information.</cntper><cntorg>REQUIRED: The organization responsible for the metadata information.</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>REQUIRED: The mailing and/or physical address for the organization or individual.</addrtype><city>REQUIRED: The city of the address.</city><state>REQUIRED: The state or province of the address.</state><postal>REQUIRED: The ZIP or other postal code of the address.</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>REQUIRED: The telephone number by which individuals can speak to the organization or individual.</cntvoice></cntinfo></metc><metd Sync="TRUE">20050330</metd><metextns><onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink><metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns></metainfo><mdLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></mdLang><mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><distinfo><resdesc Sync="TRUE">Downloadable Data</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><transize Sync="TRUE">12.310</transize><dssize Sync="TRUE">12.310</dssize></digtinfo></digform></stdorder></distinfo><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\nicknet.env.duke.edu\network\class\spring-2008\environ265\265_data\lab04_benthic_habitat_modeling\kelp99_c</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">12.310</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><spdoinfo><direct Sync="TRUE">Vector</direct><ptvctinf><esriterm Name="kelp99_c"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom Sync="TRUE">Polygon</efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">85345</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">TRUE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm><sdtsterm Name="kelp99_c"><sdtstype Sync="TRUE">G-polygon</sdtstype><ptvctcnt Sync="TRUE">85345</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><cordsysn><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><projcsn Sync="TRUE">Albers Conical Equal Area</projcsn></cordsysn><geodetic><horizdn Sync="TRUE">North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips Sync="TRUE">Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis Sync="TRUE">6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat Sync="TRUE">298.257222</denflat></geodetic><planar><planci><plance Sync="TRUE">coordinate pair</plance><plandu Sync="TRUE">meters</plandu><coordrep><absres Sync="TRUE">0.000128</absres><ordres Sync="TRUE">0.000128</ordres></coordrep></planci><mapproj><mapprojn Sync="TRUE">Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn><albers><stdparll Sync="TRUE">34.000000</stdparll><stdparll Sync="TRUE">40.500000</stdparll><longcm Sync="TRUE">-120.000000</longcm><latprjo Sync="TRUE">0.000000</latprjo><feast Sync="TRUE">0.000000</feast><fnorth Sync="TRUE">-4000000.000000</fnorth></albers></mapproj></planar></horizsys></spref><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode Sync="TRUE">Albers Conical Equal Area</identCode></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><topLvl><TopoLevCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></TopoLevCd></topLvl><geometObjs Name="kelp99_c"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">85345</geoObjCnt></geometObjs></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><eainfo><detailed Name="kelp99_c"><enttyp><enttypl Sync="TRUE">kelp99_c</enttypl><enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">85345</enttypc></enttyp><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">FID</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Shape</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Class</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Class</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">20</attwidth></attr></detailed></eainfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20050330</mdDateSt></metadata>
